Manabendra Saharia

Last Updated: February 5, 2021

Current Affiliation and Address

Assistant Professor V-318, Department of Civil Engineering Indian Institute of Technology Delhi Hauz Khas, Delhi 110016, India

Email: msaharia@iitd.ac.in | msaharia@live.com

IIT Delhi Research Group: https://hydrosenselab.github.io/

Personal Website: https://www.msaharia.com/

Office Phone: +91-011-26591260

Research Bio

The goal of my research is to develop solutions that reduce the impact of natural disasters. This involves simulating and investigating the terrestrial hydrological cycle using physics-based and data-driven models. Current focus is to develop techniques and systems for monitoring and mitigating water-related natural hazards such as floods and droughts, with a special focus on the worst-affected regions of the world.

Research Interests

Land surface modeling, flood forecasting, radar and satellite precipitation, statistics, machine Learning, crowdsourcing etc.

Professional Experience

- 2019-Present Assistant Professor, Dept. of Civil Engineering, Indian Institute of Technology Delhi.
 - 2019 Postdoctoral Research Associate, NASA Goddard Space Flight Center, USA.
 - o A West Africa Land Data Assimilation System for Forecasting Extreme Hydrological Events
 - 2017–2018 Postdoctoral Researcher, National Center for Atmospheric Research, Colorado, USA.
 - Developing a real-time and distributed HUC-based modeling system for ensemble streamflow forecasting over large domains.
 - Uncertainty quantification and sensitivity analysis of flood frequency estimates.
 - 2013–2017 **Graduate Research Assistant**, *Advanced Radar Research Center*, US National Weather Center/The University of Oklahoma.
 - 2011–2013 **Graduate Research Assistant**, *HWRL*, University of Texas at Arlington.

Education

- 2013–2017 Ph.D. in Water Resources Engineering, University of Oklahoma, Norman, OK.
 - Dissertation: Characterization and Prediction of Flash Flood Severity.
- 2011–2013 M.S. in Water Resources Engineering, University of Texas at Arlington, Arlington, TX.
 - Thesis: Ensemble Streamflow Forecasting For The Upper Trinity River Basin In Texas
- 2007–2011 B.Tech. in Civil Engineering, National Institute of Technology, Silchar, Assam, India.
 - Major Project: Flood Forecasting in Multiple River Sections using Artificial Neural Networks

Journal Publications [Under Review]

- 1. **Saharia, M.**, Jain, A., Baishya, R.R., Haobam, S., Sreejith OP, DS Pai, and Rafieeinasab, A. 2020. "India Flood Inventory: Creation of a multi-source national geospatial database to facilitate comprehensive flood research", EarthArXiv Pre-print: https://doi.org/10.31223/X5XS3V
- 2. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, P.E., Vergara, H., Gourley, J.J., Hong, Y., 2020. "Impact of rainfall spatial variability on flash flood severity".
- 3. Kiran, S. K. Saharia, M., Kirstetter, P.E., 2020. "Characterization of Floods at a Global Scale".
- 4. Potdar, A. S., Kirstetter, P.E., Wood, D., and **Saharia, M.**, 2020. "Towards Predicting Flood Peak Discharge using Machine Learning".
- 5. Newman, A.J., Stone, A.G., **Saharia, M.**, Holman, K.D., Addor, N., and Clark, M., 2020 "Identifying Sensitivities in Flood Frequency Analyses using a Stochastic Hydrologic Modeling System".

Journal Publications

- Sunghee Kim, Sadeghi, H., Limon, R.A., Saharia, M., Seo, D.J., Philpott, A., Bell, F., Brown, J., He, K., 2018 "Assessing the Skill of Medium-Range Ensemble Precipitation and Streamflow Forecasts from the Hydrologic Ensemble Forecast Service (HEFS) for the Upper Trinity River Basin in North Texas", Journal of Hydrometeorology, 19, 1467–1483
- 2. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, P.E., Vergara, H., Gourley, J.J., Hong, Y., 2017. "Characterization of Floods in the United States", Journal of Hydrology 548, 524–535.
- 3. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, P.E., Vergara, H., Gourley, J.J., Hong, Y., Giroud, M., 2017. "Mapping Flash Flood Severity in the United States", Journal of Hydrometeorology, 18, 397–411.
- 4. Li, W., Liu, C., Hong, Y., Zhang, X., Wan, Z., **Saharia, M.**, Sun, W., Yao, D., Chen, W., Chen, S., others, 2016. "A public Cloud-based China's Landslide Inventory Database (CsLID): development, zone, and spatiotemporal analysis for significant historical events, 1949-2011", Journal of Mountain Science 13, 1275–1285.
- 5. Li, W., Liu, C., Hong, Y., **Saharia, M.**, Sun, W., Yao, D., Chen, W., 2016. "Rainstorm-induced shallow landslides process and evaluation—a case study from three hot spots, China", Geomatics, Natural Hazards and Risk, 1–11.
- Zhang, Y., Hong, Y., Wang, X., Gourley, J.J., Xue, X., Saharia, M., Ni, G., Wang, G., Huang, Y., Chen, S., others, 2014. "Hydrometeorological Analysis and Remote Sensing of Extremes: Was the July 2012 Beijing Flood Event Detectable and Predictable by Global Satellite Observing and Global Weather Modeling Systems?", Journal of Hydrometeorology.
- 7. Shen, Y., Xiong, A., Hong, Y., Yu, J., Pan, Y., Chen, Z., **Saharia, M.**, 2014. "Uncertainty analysis of five satellite-based precipitation products and evaluation of three optimally merged multi-algorithm products over the Tibetan Plateau", International Journal of Remote Sensing 35, 6843–6858.
- 8. Roy, P., **Saharia, M.**, Choudhury, P., 2014. River Reaches Flood Flow Prediction using PRNN Models. International Journal of Civil, Structural, Environmental and Infrastructure Engineering Research and Development (IJCSEIERD) 1, 119–126.
- 9. **Saharia, M.**, Bhattacharjya, R.K., 2012. "Geomorphology-based time-lagged recurrent neural networks for runoff forecasting", KSCE Journal of Civil Engineering 16, 862–869.
- 10. Jain, S.K., Kumar, V., **Saharia, M.**, 2012. "Analysis of Rainfall and Temperature trends in North-East India", International Journal of Climatology.

Book Chapters

- 1. **Saharia, M.**, Li, L., Hong, Y., Wang, J., Adler, R. F., Policelli, F. S., Shahid, H., Irwn, D., Korme, T., and Okello, L. (2016). "Real-time hydrologic prediction system in East Africa through SERVIR", Hydrologic Remote Sensing Capacity Building for Sustainability and Resilience, CRC Press, Taylor and Francis Group.
- 2. Shen, Y., Anyuan, X., Hong, Y., Jingjing, Y., Yang, P., Zhuoqi, C., and Saharia, M. (2016).

"Uncertainty Analysis of Five Satellite-Based Precipitation Products and Evaluation of Three Optimally Merged Multi-algorithm Products over the Tibetan Plateau", Hydrologic Remote Sensing - Capacity Building for Sustainability and Resilience, CRC Press, Taylor and Francis Group.

Grants and Fellowships

As Principal Investigator (PI)				
Funding Agency	Project Title	Amount	Duration	Awarded
UCL-IITD Strategic Part-	Making local knowledge matter for landslides	Rs 5,00,000	1 year	2020
ner Fund	and flooding preparedness			
Principal Scientific Ad-	Developing a real-time localized flood aware-	Rs 11,00,000	1 year	2020
viser to the Govt. of Indianess system for National Capital Region				
	(NCR) using citizen science and satellite re-			
	mote sensing			
High Performance Com-	Establishing an LDAS over India	Rs 50,000	1 year	2020
puting, IIT Delhi				
IRD, IIT Delhi	New Faculty Grant	Rs 100,000		2019
IIT Delhi	Young Faculty Incentive Fellowship	Rs 25,000 p.m.	3 years	2019
National Center for Atmo-	Early Career Scientist Assembly (ECSA)	\$2000		2018
spheric Research (NCAR)	Award			
USA				

Invited Talks [Technical]

- 15 July 2020 "Role of Machine Learning in Civil Engineering", Faculty Development Program, Jorhat Engineering College, Assam.
- 20 Nov 2019 "Flood Defense Plausible solutions rather than possible", *Transforming NE region through Science and Technology Interventions*, Assam Administrative Staff College, Guwahati.
- 15 Nov 2019 "A Water Alliance for Tomorrow", River-research to Evolve Sustainable-projects for People with Eco-friendly Climate-resilient Technology (RESPECT), IIT Guwahati.

Awards and Mentions

- Mar 2017 Citation and cash award in the oral presentation category of the Student Water Conference, Oklahoma Water Resources Center, Mar 23, 2017.
- Mar 2017 Advanced Radar Research Center Student Paper Cash Award in recognition of research accomplishments and scholarly publication
- Feb 2017 First prize and cash award in the oral presentation category of the Student Research and Creativity Day, University of Oklahoma, Feb 24, 2017.
- Jan 2017 Advanced Radar Research Center Student Paper Cash Award in recognition of research accomplishments and scholarly publication
- Mar 2016 First prize and cash award in the oral presentation category of the Student Research and Creativity Day, University of Oklahoma, March 4, 2016.
- Oct 2015 Student Recognition, President's Monthly Research and Development Highlights, Volume 10, Issue 7, University of Oklahoma
- Oct 2015 Best Poster Award in the Graduate Student Poster Contest, Annual Meeting of the Society of Environmental Journalists (SEJ), Norman, October 7-11, 2015

Conference Presentations

(This list is no longer updated)

- 1. Newman, A.J., **Saharia, M.**, Stone, A., Holmes, K. (2019) "Understanding uncertainty contributions throughout the hydrologic modeling system in stochastic flood frequency analysis", AMS Annual Meeting, Phoenix, USA.
- Wood, A.W., Saharia, M., Clark E., Clark, M., Nijssen, B., (2019) "Application of an Ensemble Modeling Approach for Assimilating Observations to Improve Hydrologic and Streamflow Predictions", AMS Annual Meeting, Phoenix, USA.
- 3. **Saharia, M.**, Newman, A.J., Stone, A., Holmes, K. (2018) "Identifying potentially neglected sources of uncertainty in flood frequency estimation using a multi-model framework", AGU Annual Meeting 2018, Washington DC. [Selected for Oral]
- 4. Wood, A.W., Clark E., **Saharia, M.**, Clark, M., Nijssen, B., (2018) "Application of an ensemble-based modeling approach for assimilating observations to improve hydrologic and streamflow predictions", AGU Annual Meeting 2018, Washington DC. [Oral]
- Wood, A.W., Saharia, M., Clark, M., Bennett, A., Nijssen, B., Clark, E., Newman, A. (2018)
 "Development and Demonstration of Ensemble Hydrologic Data Assimilation Strategies for a Real-Time Distributed Regional Hydrologic Forecast System", AMS Annual Meeting 2018, Austin, Texas. [Oral]
- 6. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, PE, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y (2018) "Accounting for rainfall spatial variability in the prediction of flash floods", AMS Annual Meeting 2018, Austin, Texas. **[Poster]**
- 7. **Saharia, M.**, Wood, A.W., Clark, M., Bennett, A., Nijssen, B., Clark, E., Newman, A. (2017) "Distributed HUC-based modeling with SUMMA for ensemble streamflow forecasting over large regional domains", AGU Annual Meeting 2017 **[Poster]**
- 8. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, PE, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y. (2017) "Impact of Rainfall Spatial Variability on Flash Flood Severity", Student Water Conference, Oklahoma Water Resources Center, Mar 23-24, Oklahoma. **[Oral presentation award]**
- 9. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, PE, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y. (2017) "Impact of Rainfall Spatial Variability on Flash Flood Severity", EGU General Assembly, Apr 23-28, Austria. **[Oral]**
- Saharia, M., Kirstetter, PE, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y. (2017) "How can we measure the severity of flash floods?", Research and Creativity Day, Feb 24, University of Oklahoma. [Best Oral Presentation award]
- 11. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, PE, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y. (2016) "Accounting for Rainfall Spatial Variability in Prediction of Flash Floods", AGU Fall Meeting, Dec 12-16, San Francisco. **[Oral]**
- 12. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, PE, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y. (2016) "Accounting for Rainfall Spatial Variability in Prediction of Flash Floods", 9th European Conference on Radar in Meteorology, Oct 10, Turkey. **[Oral]**
- 13. Hong, Y., Gourley, JJ., **Saharia, M.**, Flamig, Z., Clark, R., Zhang, K., Muthike, Denus., Hasan, Emad., Cappelaere, P., Frye, S., Handy, M., Nyaga, J. (2016) "Forecasting and Communicating Water-Related Disasters in Africa", SAGE, Nepal. **[Poster]**
- 14. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, PE, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y. (2016) "Mapping the flashiest regions of the United States", Research and Creativity Day, Mar 4 University of Oklahoma. [Best Oral Presentation award]
- 15. Kirstetter, PE., **Saharia, M.**, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y. (2016) "Toward estimating the probability of flood severity over the United States", AMS Annual Meeting, 2016, New Orleans.[Oral]
- 16. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, PE, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y. (2015) "Mapping Flash Flood Severity in the United States", AGU Fall Meeting, Dec 14-18, San Francisco, California. **[Oral]**
- 17. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, PE, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y. (2015) "Where are the flashiest basins of the United States?", Annual Meeting of the Society of Environmental Journalists (SEJ), Oct 7-11, Norman, Oklahoma. [Poster] [Best Poster Award]

- 18. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, PE, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y. (2015) "Characterization and Prediction of Flash Flood Severity in the United States", 2015 International Symposium on Earth-Science Challenges, Sep 20-23, Norman, Oklahoma. **[Oral]**
- 19. **Saharia, M.**, Kirstetter, PE, Gourley, JJ., Vergara, H. and Hong, Y. (2014) "Characterization of Floods in the United States", AGU Fall Meeting, Dec 15-19, San Francisco, California. [Poster]
- 20. **Saharia, M.**, Seo., Dong-Jun, Corby, R. and He, K. (2013) "Short-range ensemble streamflow forecasting of the Upper Trinity River Evaluation via hindcasting experiments", AGU Meeting of the Americas, May 14-17, Cancun, Mexico. **[Oral]**
- 21. **Saharia, M.**, Seo., Dong-Jun, Corby, R. and Bell,F. (2013) "Increasing lead time in short-range streamflow forecasting via the Hydrologic Ensemble Forecast Service (HEFS)", NWS/OHD Seminar, Silver Spring, MD.
- 22. **Saharia, M.**, Bhattacharjya, R. K. and Satish, M. (2011) "Catchment Runoff Forecasting using Time-Lagged Recurrent Neural Networks".4th ASCE-EWRI International Perspective on Water Resources & the Environment (IPWE 2011), January 4-6, National University of Singapore, Singapore.
- 23. Roy, P., Choudhury, P. and **Saharia, M.** (2011). "River Reaches Flood Flow Prediction using TLRN models". 4th ASCE-EWRI International Perspective on Water Resources & the Environment (IPWE 2011), January 4-6, National University of Singapore, Singapore.
- 24. **Saharia, M.** and Bhattacharjya. R. K. (2011). "Comparison of ANN-based Runoff-prediction Models Trained by Eight Different Learning Algorithms".4th ASCE-EWRI International Perspective on Water Resources & the Environment (IPWE 2011), January 4-6, National University of Singapore, Singapore.
- 25. Roy, P., Choudhury, P. and **Saharia, M.** (2010). "Dynamic ANN Modeling for Flood Forecasting in a River Network". International Conference on Modeling, Optimization and Computing (ICMOC 2010), American Institute of Physics Conf. Proc., NIT Durgapur, India.

Teaching Experience

- Instructor, CVL 282 Engineering Hydrology, IIT Delhi, 2019-20, 2020-21
- Instructor, CVL 381 Design of Hydraulic Structures, IIT Delhi, 2019-20
- Instructor, CVP 731 Simulation Lab II, IIT Delhi, 2019-20
- Instructor, CVP 731 NEN 100 Professional Ethics and Social Responsibility, IIT Delhi, 2019-20
- Teaching Assistant and co-taught, CEES 5843 Hydrology Co-taught and organized lecture series, University of Oklahoma, Spring 2017
- Teaching Assistant, CEES 5903 Remote Sensing Hydrology, University of Oklahoma, Spring 2016

Ongoing Thesis Supervision

Ph.D.

- o Ravi Raj [2019-]
- Sai Kiran Kuntla [2020-]
- Bhanu Magotra [2020-]
- Anagha P. [2020-]
- Nirdesh Sharma [2020-]

M.Tech.

Khusboo Alvi [2020-21]

B.Tech.

Jatin Ahuja [2020-21]

- Yash Gupta [2020-21]
- Gautam Kunwar [2020-21]

Academic Service

Conferences

- 2020 Technical Committee, International Conference on Sustainable Water Resources Management (SWARM), Guwahati
- 2019 Conference Co-Chair, Computer Vision for Atmospheric Events Analysis (CVAE), ACPR 2019 Workshop, Auckland, New Zealand

Reviewer

- Journal of Hydrology
- Water Resources Research
- Journal of Hydrometeorology
- Journal of Flood Risk Management

Administrative Experience

Institute Level, IIT Delhi

- 2019-20 Institute Representative, JEE (Joint Entrance Examination) Advanced, IIT Delhi
- 2019-20 Institute Representative, GATE (Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering), IIT Delhi

Department Level, Department of Civil Engineering, IIT Delhi 2020-21

- Water Resources Simulation Laboratory I/C (Jointly)
- CVN 101 Intro to Civil Engineering (Coordinator)
- CVQ 301 Civil Engineering Seminar (Co-Coordinator)
- NEN 101 Professional Ethics and Social Responsibility (Department Volunteer)
- 2020-21 B.Tech. Report Evaluation Committee (Jointly)

Popular Writing

- 1. **Saharia, Manabendra** "Can a Sanctuary in Brahmaputra Save River Dolphins?", Nov 29, 2016. The Assam Tribune (Lead editorial)
- 2. **Saharia, Manabendra** "An ASEAN university in North-East", Mar 8, 2016. The Assam Tribune (Editorial)

Professional Memberships

- American Geophysical Union
- American Meteorological Society
- American Society of Civil Engineers

Workshops Participated

- Oct 2019 River-research to Evolve Sustainable-Projects for People with Eco-friendly Climate-resilient Technology (RESPECT), IIT Guwahati
- Sep 2017 The 2016 Multi-Radar/Multi-Sensor (MRMS) HMT-Hydro Testbed Experiment (Served as Coordinator)

- May-Jul 2015 National Flood Interoperability Experiment, Summer Institute, National Water Center, Tuscaloosa, Alabama (8 Weeks)
 - Jan 2011 HEPEX Workshop, National Weather Center, Silver Spring, Maryland (3 days)

Personal Interests

Educational outreach, mentoring, volunteering, writing columns, Fitness